Not at home.
In the meanwhile the dwarves sat in darkness, and utter silence fell about
them. Little they ate and little they spoke. They could not count the passing
of time, and they scarcely dared to move, for the whisper of their voices
echoed and rustled in the tunnel. If they do, they woke still to darkness and
to silence, going on unbroken. At last, after days and days of waiting, as it
seemed, when they were becoming choked and dazed for one of air, they could
bear it no longer. They would almost have welcomed sounds from below of the
dragon's return. In the silence they feared some cunning devilry of his, but
they could not sit there forever. Thorin spoke. "Let us try the door," he said. I
must feel the wind on my face soon or die. I think I would rather be smashed
by smog in the open than suffocate in here. So several of the dwarves got up
and groped back to where the door had been. But they found that the upper end
of the tunnel had been shattered and blocked with broken rock. Neither key
nor the magic it had once obeyed would ever open that door again. "We are
trapped," they groaned. "This is the end. We shall die here.
But somehow, just when the dwarves were most desparing, Bilbo felt a strange
lightning of the heart, as if a heavy weight had gone from under his waist
coat. "Come, come," he said. "While there is life, there's hope," as my
father used to say, "and third time pays for all. I am going down the tunnel once
again. I have been that way twice when I knew there was a dragon at the other
end. So I will risk a third visit when I am no longer sure. Anyway, the only way
out is down. And I think this time you had better all come with me. In
desperation they agreed, and Thoren was the first to go forward by Bilbo's side.
Now do be careful, whispered the Hobbit.
And as quiet as you can be. There may be no smog at the bottom, but then again
there may be. Don't let us take any unnecessary risks.
Down, down they went, the dwarves could not of course compare with the hobbit in
real stealth, and they made a deal of puffing and shuffling, which echoes
magnified alarmingly. But though every now and again Bilbo in fear stopped and
listened, not a sound stirred below.
near the bottom as well as he could judge. Bilbo slipped on his ring and
went ahead, but he did not need it. The darkness was complete, and they were all
invisible. Ring or no ring. In fact, so black was it that the hobbit came to the
opening unexpectedly, put his hand on air, stumbled forward, and rolled
headlong into the hole. There he lay face downwards on the floor, and did not
dare to get up, or hardly even to breathe.
But nothing moved.
There was not a gleam of light unless, as it seemed to him, when at last he
slowly raised his head, there was a pale white glint above him, and far off in the gloom.
But certainly it was not a spark of dragon fire, though the worm stench was
heavy in the place, and the taste of vapor was on his tongue. At length Mr.
Baggins could bear it no longer.
Confound you, smog, you worm. He squeaked aloud. Stop playing hide and
seek. Give me a light and then eat me if you can catch me. Faint echoes ran round
the unseen hall, but there was no answer. Bilbo got up and found that he
did not know in what direction to turn.
Now I wonder what on earth Smal is playing at, he said. He is not at home
today or tonight or whatever it is. I do believe if One and Gloin have not lost
their tinder boxes, perhaps we can make a little light and have a look round
before the luck turns.
Light? He cried. Can anybody make a light? The dwarves, of course, were very
alarmed when Bilbo fell forward down the step with a bump into the hall, and they
sat huddled just where he had left them at the end of the tunnel. "Shash!" they
hissed when they heard his voice. And though that helped the hobbit to find
out where they were, it was some time before he could get anything else out of
them. But in the end, when Bilbo actually began to stamp on the floor and
screamed out, "Light at the top of his shrill voice, Thorin gave way, and One
and Glowin were sent back to their bundles at the top of the tunnel. After
a while, a twinkling gleam showed them returning. Oin with a small pine torto
light in his hand and glowing with a bundle of others under his arm. Quickly
Bilbo trotted to the door and took the torch, but he could not persuade the
dwarves to light the others or to come and join him yet. As Thoren carefully
explained, Mr. Baggins was still officially their expert burglar and
investigator. If he liked to risk a light, that was his affair. They would
wait in the tunnel for his report. So they sat near the door and watched. They
saw the little dark shape of the hobbit start across the floor, holding his tiny
light aloft. Every now and again, while he was still near enough, they caught a
glint and a tinkle as he stumbled on some golden thing. The light grew
smaller as he wandered away into the vast hole. Then it began to rise,
dancing into the air. Bilbo was climbing the great mound of treasure. Soon he
stood upon the top and still went on.
Then they saw him halt and stoop for a moment, but they did not know the
reason. It was the Arkan Stone, the heart of the mountain. So Bilbo guessed
from Thoren's description. But indeed there could not be two such gems, even
in so marvelous a horde, even in all the world. Ever as he climbed, the same
white gleam had shone before him, and drawn his feet towards it. Slowly it
grew to a little globe of palid light.
Now as he came near, it was tinged with a flickering sparkle of many colors at
the surface, reflected and splintered from the wavering light of his torch. At
last he looked down upon it, and he caught his breath. The great jewel shown
before his feet of its own inner light, and yet cut and fashioned by the
dwarves, who had dug it from the heart of the mountain long ago, it took all
light that fell upon it, and changed it into 10,000 sparks of white radiance
shot with glints of the rainbow.
Suddenly, Bilbo's arm went towards it, drawn by its enchantment. His small hand
would not close about it, for it was a large and heavy gem, but he lifted it,
shut his eyes, and put it in his deepest pocket.
Now I am a burglar indeed, thought he, but I suppose I must tell the dwarves
about it sometime. They did say I could pick and choose my own share, and I
think I would choose this if they took all the rest. All the same, he had an
uncomfortable feeling that the picking and choosing had not really been meant
to include this marvelous gem, and that trouble would yet come of it. Now he
went on again, down the other side of the great mound he climbed, and the
spark of his torch vanished from the sight of the watching dwarves.
But soon they saw it far away in the distance again.
Bilbo was crossing the floor of the hall. He went on until he came to the
great doors at the further side, and there a draft of air refreshed him, but
it almost puffed out his light. He peeped timidly through and caught a
glimpse of great passages and of the dim beginnings of wide stairs going up into
the gloom, and still there was no sight nor sound of smog. He was just going to
turn and go back when a black shape swooped at him and brushed his face. He
squeaked and started, stumbled backwards and fell. His torch dropped head
downwards and went out. "Only a bat, I suppose, and hope," he said miserably.
"But now what am I to do? Which is east, south, north, or west." "Thoren, Balin,
O going, Killy!" He cried as loud as he could. It seemed a thin little noise in
the wide blackness. The lights gone out.
Someone come and find me and help me.
For the moment his courage had failed altogether.
Faintly the dwarves heard his small cries, though the only word they could
catch was, "Help!" "Now what on earth or under it has happened," said Thoren.
"Certainly not the dragon, or he would not go on squeaking." They waited a
moment or two, and still there were no dragon noises, no sound at all, in fact,
but Bilbo's distant voice. Come, one of you, get another light or two. Thorin
ordered. It seems we have got to go and help our burglar. It is about our turn
to help, said Balin. And I am quite willing to go. Anyway, I expect it is
safe for the moment. Glowing lit several more torches, and then they all crept
out one by one, and went along the wall as hurriedly as they could. It was not
long before they met Bilbo himself coming back towards them. His wits had
quickly returned as soon as he saw the twinkle of their lights. "Only a bat and
a dropped torch." "Nothing worse," he said in answer to their questions.
Though they were much relieved, they were inclined to be grumpy at being
frightened for nothing. But what they would have said if he had told them at
that moment about the Arkham Stone, I don't know. The mere fleeting glimpses
of treasure which they had caught as they went along had rekindled all the
fire of their dwarvish hearts. And when the heart of a dwarf, even the most
respectable, is wakened by gold and by jewels, he grows suddenly bold, and he
may become fierce. The dwarves indeed no longer needed any urging. All were now
eager to explore the hall while they had the chance and willing to believe that
for the present smalle.
Each now gripped a lighted torch, and as they gazed first on one side and then on
another, they forgot fear and even caution. They spoke aloud and cried out
to one another as they lifted old treasures from the mound or from the
wall and held them in the light, caressing and fingering them. Feelely
and Killy were almost in merry mood, and finding still hanging there many golden
harps strung with silver, they took them and struck them, and being magical and
also untouched by the dragon, who had small interest in music, they were still in tune.
The dark hall was filled with a melody that had long been silent, but most of
the dwarves were more practical. They gathered gems and stuffed their pockets,
and let what they could not carry fall back to their fingers with a sigh.
Thoren was not least among these, but always he searched from side to side for
something which he could not find. It was the arkan stone,
but he spoke of it yet to no one. Now the dwarves took down mail and weapons
from the walls and armed themselves.
Royal indeed did Thor in look, clad in a coat of goldplated rings with a silver
hafted axe and a belt crusted with scarlet stones.
Mr. Baggins, he cried, here's the first payment of your reward. Cast off your
old coat and put on this. With that he put on Bilbo a small coat of male
wrought for some young elf prince long ago. It was of silver steel which the
elves call mithil, and with it went a belt of pearls and crystals. A light
helm of figured leather strengthened beneath with hoops of steel and studded
about the brim with white gems was set upon the hobbit's head. I feel
magnificent, he thought, but I expect I look rather absurd, how they would laugh
on the hill at home. Still, I wish there was a looking glass handy.
All the same, Mr. Baggins kept his head more clear of the bewitchment of the
horde than the dwarves did. Long before the dwarves were tired of examining the
treasures, he became weary of it, and sat down on the floor, and he began to
wonder nervously what the end of it all would be. I would give a good many of
these precious goblets, he thought, for a drink of something cheering out of one
of Bjorn's wooden bowls.
Corin, he cried aloud. What next? We are armed, but what good has any armor ever
been before against Smouled the dreadful? This treasure is not yet won
back. We are not looking for gold yet, but for a way of escape, and we have
tempted luck too long. You speak the truth," answered Doran, recovering his
wits. "Let us go. I will guide you. Not in a thousand years should I forget the
ways of this palace." Then he hailed the others, and they gathered together, and
holding their torches above their heads, they passed through the gaping doors,
not without many a backward glance of longing. Their glittering male they had
covered again with their old cloaks and their bright helms with their tattered
hoods. And one by one they walked behind Thoren, a line of little lights in the
darkness that halted often, listening in fear once more for any rumor of the
dragon's coming. Though all the old adornments were long mouldered or
destroyed, and though all was befouled and blasted with the comingings and
goings of the monster, Thoren knew every passage and every turn. They climbed
long stairs and turned and went down wide echoing ways and turned again and
climbed yet more stairs and yet more stairs again. These were smooth cut out
of the living rock broad and fair. And up up the dwarves went and they met no
sign of any living thing, only fur of shadows that fled from the approach of
their torches fluttering in the drafts.
The steps were not made all the same for Hobbit legs, and Bilbo was just feeling
that he could go on no longer, when suddenly the roof sprang high and far
beyond the reach of their torch light. A white glimmer could be seen coming
through some opening far above, and the air smelt sweeter.
Before them, light came dimly through great doors that hung twisted on their
hinges and half burnt. This is the great chamber of thr, said Thoren. The hall of
feasting and of council. Not far off now is the front gate. They passed through
the ruined chamber. Tables were rotting there. Cheers and benches were lying
there overturned, charred and decaying.
Skulls and bones were upon the floor among flagans and bowls, and broken
drinking horns and dust. As they came through yet more doors at the further
end, a sound of water fell upon their ears, and the gray light grew suddenly
more full. "There is the birth of the running river," said Doran. "From here
it hastens to the gate. Let us follow it." "Out of a dark opening in a wall of
rock, there issued a boiling water, and it flowed swirling in a narrow channel,
carved and made straight and deep by the cunning of ancient hands. Beside it ran
a stone-paved road, wide enough for many men a breast. Swiftly along this they
ran, and round a wide sweeping turn, and behold, before them stood the broad light of
day. In front there rose a tall arch, still showing the fragments of old
carvin work within, worn and splintered and blackened, though it was. A misty
sun sent its pale light between the arms of the mountain, and beams of gold fell
on the pavement at the threshold. A whirl of bats, frightened from slumber
by their smoking torches, flurried over them. As they sprang forward, their feet
slithered on stones, rubbed smooth and slimed by the passing of the dragon. Now
before them, the water fell noisily outward and foamed down towards the
valley. They flung their pale torches to the ground and stood gazing out with
dazzled eyes. They were come to the front gate and were looking out upon
Dale. Well, said Bilbo, I never expected to be looking out of this door, and I
never expected to be so pleased to see the sun again, and to feel the wind on
my face. But ow, this wind is cold. It was. A bitter easterly breeze blew with
a threat of oncoming winter. It swirled over and round the arms of the mountain
into the valley and sighed among the rocks. After their long time in the
stewing depths of the dragon haunted caverns, they shivered in the sun.
Suddenly Bilbo realized that he was not only tired but also very hungry indeed.
It seems to be late morning, he said, and so I suppose it is more or less
breakfast time if there is any breakfast to have. But I don't feel that Smal's
front doorstep is the safest place for a meal. Do let's go somewhere where we can
sit quiet for a bit. Quite right, said Balin. And I think I know which way we
should go. We ought to make for the old lookout post at the southwest corner of
the mountain. How far is that? Asked the hobbit.
5 hours march, I should think. It will be rough going. The road from the gate
along the left edge of the stream seems all broken up, but look down there. The
river loops suddenly east across Dale in front of the ruined town. At that point
there was once a bridge leading to steep stairs that climbed up the right bank
and so to a road running towards Ravenhill. There is or was a path that
left the road and climbed up to the post. A hard climb too, even if the old
steps are still there.
Dear me," grumbled the hobbit, "More walking and more climbing without
breakfast. I wonder how many breakfasts and other meals we have missed inside
that nasty clockless timeless whole." As a matter of fact, two nights and the day
between had gone by, and not altogether without food, since the dragon smashed
the magic door. But Bilbo had quite lost count, and it might have been one night
or a week of nights for all he could tell.
Come, come," said Borin, laughing. His spirits had begun to rise again, and he
rattled the precious stones in his pockets. "Don't call my palace a nasty
hole. You wait till it has been cleaned and redecorated."
"That won't be till Smout dead," said Bilbo glumbly. "In the meanwhile, where
is he? I would give a good breakfast to know. I hope he is not up on the
mountain looking down at us." That idea disturbed the dwarfs mightily, and they
quickly decided that Bilbo and Balon were right. We must move away from here,
said Dory. I feel as if his eyes were on the back of my head. It's a cold,
lonesome place, said Bomb. There may be drink, but I see no sign of food. A
dragon would always be hungry in such parts.
Come on, come on, cried the others. Let us follow Balin's path. Under the rocky
wall to the right, there was no path. So on they trudged among the stones on the
left side of the river, and the emptiness and desolation soon sobered
even Thorin again. The bridge that Balon had spoken of they found long fallen,
and most of its stones were now only boulders in the shallow, noisy stream.
But they forded the water without much difficulty, and found the ancient steps
and climbed the high bank. After going a short way, they struck the old road, and
before long came to a deep dell, sheltered among the rocks. There they
rested for a while, and had such a breakfast as they could, chiefly cra and
water. If you want to know what cre is, I can only say that I don't know the
recipe. But it is biscuitish, keeps good indefinitely, is supposed to be
sustaining, and is certainly not entertaining, being in fact very
uninteresting, except as a chewing exercise. It was made by the lakemen for long journeys.
After that they went on again, and now the road struck westwards and left the
river, and the great shoulder of the southpointing mountain spur drew ever
nearer. At length they reached the hill path. It scrambled steeply up, and they
plotted slowly, one behind the other, till at last, in the late afternoon,
they came to the top of the ridge, and saw the wintry sun going downwards to
the west. Here they found a flat place without a wall on three sides, but
backed to the north by a rocky face, in which there was an opening, like a door.
From that door there was a wide view, east and south, and west. Here, said
Balon. In the old days we used always to keep watchmen, and that door behind
leads into a rock huneed chamber that was made here is a guard room. There
were several places like it round the mountain, but there seems small need for
watching in the days of our prosperity, and the guards were made over
comfortable. Perhaps otherwise we might have had longer warning of the coming of
the dragon, and things might have been different. Still here we can now lie
head and sheltered for a while and can see much without being seen.
Not much use if we have been seen coming here, said Dory, who was always looking
up towards the mountains peak as if he expected to see Smog perched there like
a bird on a steeple.
We must take our chance of that, said Thorin. We can go no further today.
Here, here," cried Bilbo, and flung himself on the ground. In the rock
chamber there would have been room for a hundred, and there was a small chamber
further in, more removed from the cold outside. It was quite deserted. Not even
wild animals seemed to have used it in all the days of Smabs Dominion. There
they laid their burdens, and some threw themselves down at once, and slept, but
the others sat near the outer door and discussed their plans. In all their talk
they came perpetually back to one thing where was smog. They looked west and
there was nothing and east there was nothing. And in the south there was no
sign of the dragon but there was a gathering of very many birds. At that
they gazed and wondered, but they were no nearer understanding it when the
first cold stars came out. Chapter 14.